Guide to the Franz Goldmann Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Franz Goldmann papers
1939-1968
MS 1318
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
1.5
(4 boxes)
Office files consisting of writings and research materials relating to his scholarly work and teaching in the field of public health. Topics covered include health insurance, Social Security, costs and social organization of medical care, home care and medical care for the elderly and the chronically ill. These papers form part of the Contemporary Medical Care and Health Policy Collection.
Goldmann, Franz
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the Dept. of Epidemiology and Public Health, Yale University.
Biographical / Historical
Physician, educator; born Elberfeld, Germany; M.D., Friedrick Wilhelms University, Berlin, 1920; came to U.S., 1937, naturalized, 1943; fellow Dept. Public Health, Yale School of Medicine, 1937-1939, associate clinical professor, 1939-1946, clinical professor, 1946-1947, lecturer 1947-1949; associate professor Harvard School Public Health, 1947-1958, emeritus professor, 1958-1970.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The Franz Goldmann Papers appear to be Goldmann's office files; they consist entirely of materials relating to his scholarly work and teaching. Those materials (correspondence, notes, drafts, reprints, and research material) which could readily be linked with a particular publication or speech by Goldmann have been arranged chronologically under the heading "Writings"; the folder title in each case represents Goldmann's final title. The remaining papers (correspondence, notes, and research material) are arranged according to subject, and alphabetized by subject name, under the heading "Source material" (Goldmann's term). These files reflect Goldmann's interest and involvement in such propblems as health insurance, Social Security, costs and social organization of medical care, home care, and medical care for the elderly and the chronically ill.
The papers were received in June 1979 from the Department of Epidemiology and Public Health.
Health services administration; Home care services; Health insurance; Medicaid; Medical care, Cost of; Older people -- Medical care; Public health; Educators; Physicians; Contemporary Medical Care and Health Policy Collection; Goldmann, Franz
- Inventory
  - Writings
    - "Recent Developments in Tax-Supported Medical Care in Great Britain", 1939 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - "Medical Care for Farmers", 1943 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - "Meeting the Family's Medical Costs", 1946 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - "Techniques for Evaluating Union Health Insurance Programs", 1946 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - "Your Community", 1946 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - "Planning a Medical Care Program for Union Members", 1947 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - "Labor's Attitude toward Health Insurance", 1947-1949 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - "Types of Health Insurance Plans", 1948 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - "Payment for Physicians' Services under Crippled Children's Programs", 1950 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - "Public Medical Care in Great Britain and Scandinavian Countries", 1950 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - "Methods of Payment for Physicians' Services in Medical Care Programs", 1951 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - "Rehabilitation under Workmen's Compensation", 1951 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - "Principles of an Effective and Economical Program of Medical Care for Elderly People", 1951-1952, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - "Home Care for the Needy and Medically Needy", 1951-1953, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - "Medical Care Statistics", 1953 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - "Multiple Screening for Chronic Disease", 1953 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - "The Quality of Medical Care Provided at the Labour Health Institute, St. Louis, Missouri", 1954 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - "Voluntary Medical Care Insurance: Achievements and Shortcomings", 1954 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - "The Garment Industry Health Center, Kansas City, Missouri" (I.L.G.W.U.), 1955 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - "The Most for Your Medical Dollar", 1955 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - "The Place of Medical Care in Public Assistance Programs", 1956 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - "The Problem of Medical Care for the Needy and Medically Needy", 1956 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - "Reasons for Prolonged Hospital Stay", 1957, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - "Role of Organized Labor in Hospital Care: Significant Attitudes, Aims and Programs of Labor", 1957 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - "Socio-Medical Aspects of Aging: A Community Challenge", 1958 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - "Voluntary Health Insurance for Senior Citizens", [1958] (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - "Residents of Homes for the Aged", 1960 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - "Short-Term Training in Home Care: Next Steps", 1967-1968 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Adequate Home Care for the Chronically Ill: A Planning Guide (notes), undated (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Notes for book on social organization and economics of medical care, undated (Box 2, Folder 30 - 31)
  - Source Material
    - Aged, 1963-1967 (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - American Arbitration Association, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - Costs of medical care, undated (Box 3, Folder 34 - 36)
    - Long-term care, 1961, 1966-1968 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - Medical economics, 1959, 1964-1968, undated (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - Problems of the physician, and the place of the physician in modern society, undated (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - Social insurance, foreign, 1949, 1962-1967 (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - Social organization of medical care: principles and problems, undated (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - Social Security amendments, 1965 (Medicaid, Medicare), undated (Box 4, Folder 42 - 44)
    - Social Security programs, 1964-1967, undated (Box 4, Folder 45)